[Music]
you're listening to the AI native Dev
brought to you by
[Music]
Tesla on today's episode joining me is
Omar rosenbalm and Omar is CTO and
co-founder of swim Omar welcome to the
session how are you I'm great thank you
thanks so much for having me here
excited to be it's an absolute pleasure
and om your your background is actually
uh a little bit in the cyber security
space as well right from from from
scratch all the way from day one all the
way through to a number of different uh
cyber security posts and roles that
you've had in the that's right that's my
initial background and my roots I would
say yeah interesting so what made you
what made you move across to the AIS and
the documentation space so actually it's
it comes from my background in also
training so I did training for cyber
security at first and then programming
and I found that Engineers even with the
best training available when they first
got onto their job in say software
organizations they were new to the
codebase and it would be a very hard
first month to get acquainted with the
codebase and how things work at this
specific company that they joined and
from encountering that challenge over
and over again I said into solving it
initially focusing on onboarding new
developers to a codebase or to a company
and gradually I realized that this
problem of knowledge hearing of
understanding the codebase is actually
always there and especially when the
organization grows and the codebase
grows they're parts of it that no one
who is actively on the team has green
themselves yeah so they're part of the
codas no one knows right yeah and it
poses great challenges and it seemed
like it's a problem that everyone in the
software industry has been living with
for a long time everyone knows this an
issue this is so true and let's start
let's even start a little bit more high
level and just like defining the term
documentation right because that can
mean different things to different
people when we talk about documentation
for code or do documentation in a
project what are the different types of
documentation that that typically you
you see people wanting to create for a
codebase or a project so first of all I
think that when we talk about
documentation we need to remember that
with a few exceptions people don't write
documentation to have documentation they
write it to share their knowledge right
for others to read and understand and
documentation is only one solution for
that and usually when people think about
documentation they think either of a
read me file so this could be a markdown
file this is how you get started with
this repo it could be client facing
documentation usually API docs this how
you call this API these are the
parameters and so on it could be some
Wiki style documents that are usually a
mix of high level explanations some
diagrams architectural diagrams and some
explanations about how things actually
work in the code people tend to leave
those relatively high level because they
know if they actually explain the code
this document will inevitably become
outdated very soon right yes that's one
of the hardest ones to keep in sync and
I think sometimes PE people have varying
levels of what they actually consider
good documentation in code because some
things are obvious from the code yet
you're almost making the code hard to
read because you're peppering with so
many comments that are obvious it
actually becomes a negative to the code
base to have so much documentation
definitely and that's is actually the
last kind of documentation that people
sometimes think of when they say
documentation is code ments which I
think are a very specific form of
documentation that have their place um
yet sometimes people think of
documentation as code comments and vice
versa and it's it's only a very small
subset yeah yeah and I mention obviously
uh you're the CTO of uh of company
called swimswim for those Googling and
and checking out we'll have links in the
show notes as well of course where where
does swim focus in their in their uh
ability to make changes to this space
and make it easier for folks right so
first if we started with the name so
we're called Swim because when we
started exploring this challenge we were
told that the way to get people on board
into a code base or get to know new
parts of the code base is by throwing
them into the water into the deep end of
the pool then they either sink or swim
and we wanted to help them to swim hence
the name and we help organizations
understand their own code and we do it
in multiple ways one is generating
documentation automatically based on the
code and static analysis you mentioned
my background in cyber secur so we take
a lot of inspiration slash technical
tools from cyber security world and
apply that to understanding the code and
then generating documentation we also
allow developers to write documentation
that is then kept up to date as the code
evolves that is easy to find so in
general what we try to do is allow you
to spend as little time as possible
conveying your knowledge to others
sharing it with others by generating a
lot of the documentation for you and
helping you focus on the things that
only you know as a developer because not
everything can be understood from code
right like why you chose this technical
approach over another approach that
isn't implemented or you do this because
a specific client asked for it in some
case and that's why this if is there so
some of these cases cannot be understood
from code no matter how much AI would
become amazing right it's like it's only
in some someone's mind and I think one
of our goals is to extra extract that
Knowledge from their minds so that other
people can know it when it's relevant
for them yeah taking the context from
someone's head is so much harder to get
to obviously than the context of what's
written down and I guess one of the
problems with documentation in general
is that's the bit that gets lost right
and as soon as that developer moves on
or or leaves or whatever it is that's
the core piece of information which
which very often is the thing which is
critical for future decision- making or
change change management and things like
that so let's go a little bit personal
here then Omar as a developer yourself
do you find documentation writing easy
fun or is it something that you put off
uh something that you
dislike so in recent years it's a superc
conscious task for me because I always
think about users of swim doing that
using swim and what their experience
would be right so it's it's it's weird
I'm trying to just write or just create
the documentation but also be in the
mind of someone else doing it personally
I'm a very weird programmer in the sense
that I actually like writing text it's
not common something that I enjoy doing
and I also enjoy sharing my knowledge I
like to teach so for me it's a form of
teaching something that I know
specifically about the code so
personally I used to not like it since
it didn't make sense to me to write
something that I know would inevitably
become
outdated once we were able to solve this
with swim I started enjoying writing
documentation and why do they become
outdated then is is this and and
obviously the reason is because people
when they make changes to code they they
don't make their equivalent change or
the corresponding change to the
documentation but why is that is that
because it's a thing that developers
don't want to do and they just enjoy
coding is that because there's just too
much pressure these days on the way
people deliver software that actually as
soon as they finished that feature they
got 10 other features that they need to
get started what's the typical inertia
for developers not to write that
documentation yeah so it's a very good
question and I think we we should
separate between updating the
documentation and not writing it in the
first place right to address your first
question about not updating the
documentation I think the underlying
issue is the fact that the docs are
decoupled from the code so as a
developer I'm in the zone I write my
feature I test it I debug it I ship it I
know that it actually affected some
document someone else has written some
time ago right or maybe that even I
wrote some time ago and I just don't
remember so I don't even know that I
need to update the documentation
definitely I wouldn't want to go through
all the documentation we have in the
organization and consider whether it
should be changed or not right so it's
almost impossible to do yeah and
regarding why you wouldn't write it so I
think it's basically three main issues
one is that it's hard to write
documentation good documentation and
most developers don't like it at all to
write text it's not something they enjoy
you need to think about how to structure
a document what's important what's not
important it's not what they like to do
they would rather code second as I felt
before swim it's pretty silly to invest
your time and effort on writing a
document that would inevitably become
outdated and third of all even if you
create a really good document and it
turned out to be up to dat the person
who needs it would most likely not find
it when they need it yeah because it's
somewhere they didn't think of looking
for it so again why bother why would I
invest my time and effort in creating
document no one would read they end up
reading it then it would be outdated by
the time they do so why bother it makes
sense to me that people don't like to
write the documentation in this reality
what's the piece that AI can assist with
here
cool so I think if we agree that say a
developer getting thrown into the water
would highly appreciate or benefit from
really good thorough documentation that
walks them through the important things
and I think almost everyone agrees on
that if you had that documentation if it
was up to date that would be great but
for reasons we mentioned no one writes
it so I think AI can actually help in
all three main issues we discussed it
can help you write a documentation in
various ways and there is a very
delicate balance here because I think
it's not like you give AI the codebase
AI will write all the docs it's too
simplified but I think AI can definitely
help a lot in that AI can help you keep
the documentation up to date as the code
changes and I can help you find the
documentation when you need it so in all
three pieces embedding AI in the right
manner which is delicate I think would
make a really big difference H and I
think that first piece that we mentioned
earlier about when you want to make a
change to documentation is that
awareness um of what what documentation
already exists um and what documentation
is relevant to the piece that I'm
changing that context the fact that AI
can take in huge amounts of context
being able to pass in large amounts of
text which is obviously one of its
wonderful things that it can consume and
read and understand that allows it to to
eliminate that aware Wess problem when
we think about the understanding though
the actual appreciation of the code
that's changing and then understanding
which parts of the documentation that's
relevant to how how accurate or how good
is it she you know bridging uh that Gap
it's a really interesting question and
actually this was the first task we set
ourselves to solve at swim and we
started it way before llms became a main
thing so our approach to that was to
actually couple parts of the code with
the corresponding documentation parts
and then track those parts of the code
as they evolve and when we track those
changes I mean we track the part of the
code that someone documented and then we
track how we changes and then we need to
decide whether it's maybe a very trivial
change we just update something
internally it might be a subtle change
that we think should be updated
automatically but perhaps the user would
want to approve the changes we're making
automatically and third it's a breaking
change so here for the breaking changes
you can say okay how often did this
happen if it doesn't happen often enough
maybe the right thing is to actually
allow the user to look right now this
was the document before this part
changed drastically you should change
this based on the PO request that is now
fresh in your mind right and maybe this
is a suggestion by AI as to what should
be here now but you are the human in the
loop and you can
make an educated decision as to how you
want the outcome to be right yeah so the
goal of AI here or an algorithm that
tracks code changes and analyzes how
significant they are is first of all to
make you aware that something that you
change corresponds to a specific
document and also to notify whether you
actually need to intervene and uh
consider the change manually
or it's easy enough to just update it
using Ai and just to let the listeners
know we'll be doing a demonstration and
a in a part two of this on YouTube which
will show a lot of this in action using
the swim tool but really talking about
the the changes in workflow or the
updates that developers need to need to
adopt to to make use of this AI
assistant or assistance through the new
workflow now when we talk about this
workflow that we're mentioning now it's
very AI assistant based right is that
because the we're at a point in time
whereby that's how developers want to
consume these changes or is that because
the autonomy of keeping documentation
aligned with the code and the
functionality changes
automatically the AI models aren't where
they need to be in order for that to
just happen in the background I think
it's a bit of both and also a third
Factor
which is sometimes you made a change and
no Ai No matter how good can know why
this is something we need to extract
from the human brain right so for that
you want the user the person to actually
consider the change and say oh actually
I did that because the product manager
asked for it because he talked with a
client and he wants to write that down
so I think ai's job here is to prompt
you by saying this is not clear why did
you do that but I need your input here
yeah and I think it's a healthy
combination or
assistance way of operating with AI in
this yeah and I think this is how
developers today are comfortably
interacting with AI as as assistance and
almost like a A Change by change uh
mechanism and it's very interesting what
you mentioned there about that kind of
like creating that tight coupling
between code and documentation so that
it's easier for for the tools and the AI
to essentially understand what it needs
to or at least it reduces the context
scope as to say this is most likely area
and that gets you I presume much more
accurate results in that reduction of
context 100% correct basically we say
this is what changed in the document and
for context you know what the entire
document was and the surrounding code
that is relevant but we know exactly
what changed because we can track the
code changes yeah got it okay and in in
terms of swim just curious out of from a
tooling point of view now in my
background actually previously at sneak
we used an amount of AI in in our tool
and we also did Static analysis do you
rely upon AI entirely for this or is
there a balance between pre-existing
like static analysis of code and and
documentation versus the AI piece that
that combines so we heavily rely on
static analysis especially for creating
documentation for multiple reasons we
think that AI is great
at some things outstanding at some
things not at everything and I think the
task of really understanding a big code
base and disambiguating even like a
small example of having a function that
appears on the same name in different
locations but it's actually a different
implementation it's something that llms
are not as good as at
understanding and I think static
analysis can really do a lot of the
heavy lifting there and provide AI with
okay this is the flow you're trying to
do for example this where it starts this
where it
goes now translate that into natural
language that is coherent and clear this
is something that AI is great at right
or llms are great at and I think this
balance is very interesting I would also
say that from a practical point of view
when you reduce the amount of calls to
say an AI agent that tries to understand
everything it's much faster and cheaper
when you can do things based on
deterministic
thetic analysis based approaches and
then there is the magic ingredient of AI
at the end of the process that turns it
into documentation or interacts with the
user with natural language and that's
where it shines yeah yeah excellent and
and I think do do you see that overtime
changing yes I think SII becomes better
at additional tasks we might want to
offload some of those tasks to AI I
think some balance would always be there
and I think there would be advantages
either practical in terms of cost and
latency or in terms of how much you want
to control the quality because if you
got a bad response from Ai and you can
keep on tweaking but at the end of the
day you're unsure what's going to happen
when you write something deterministic
you can iterate and improve it from time
to time right yeah I feel like the
balance would change but we would need
both for the foreseeable future at least
yeah and I think it's that determinism
which is the most important thing
because if allows that validation
through that analysis basically through
ways outside of AI to to validate so
that tight coupling allows us to really
avoid that drift a lot of the time in a
much more in a much more accurate way
let's talk about the workflows with the
developer though because there's
obviously a number of different ways in
which these changes can be made aware to
the developer IDE some prefer PR testing
those kind of things what what in first
of all I'd love to hear from the
experience of the vendor perspective how
they want to consume the advice the
information from a tool like
swim I think most developers vast
majority want to consume that in the IDE
as part of the workflow and get zero
Interruption and like organically find
out if they need to change something or
also if there is documentation that can
help them if we talked about finding
documentation I think from the
organizational level it's usually
important to actually enforce that all
of the documents are up to date or at
least you get visibility to whether a PO
request you're trying to merge has
impacted parts of the
documentation so that should be as part
of the PO request cicd
process yeah that's interesting actually
because very often you see a lot of
tools whereby it's you're trying to push
something into a developer workflow and
so very often it's a developer will use
an ID plug-in if they have but I think
this is a case where the value that it
actually shows them the fact that it can
actually make a developer's life easier
by reading the right documentation
before looking at the code or changing
the code in The Wider uh context
encourages a developer to want to use it
in the ID because it'll effectively save
them time in their change making it
gives them more visibility into the
changes they're making so that's really
important and yet I agree with the kind
of PR and I saw that specifically
previously in my sneak days where
companies want irrespective of whether
someone chooses or doesn't want to use a
tool in their IDE or a plugin in their
IDE it's a really good catch all to say
if you do it in your IDE there'll be no
surprises in your PR but if you don't do
it in your ID we still want to make sure
that everyone is doing it at a
sufficient level that that we expect for
the team so that in fact there is no
drift because there's no point one
developer doing this but no one else in
the team doing it everyone has to step
together in the in the workflow or
process yeah especially if a developer
uses Vim
extension to run there right and we
don't want to enforce developers to use
a specific IDE or very specific Warlow
but at the organizational level you do
want to make sure say all the
documentation is up to date or you don't
introduce vulnerabilities in your
dependencies right so you want to
enforce something in the po po request
process as well absolutely there's still
some developers somewhere who can't exit
vim and so is just choosing to use Vim
continued as their IDE so that's how
they pretend it's their choice to go
forward with but yeah absolutely let's
talk about automatic documentation now
which is another interesting thing I I
guess I would probably say more for
legacy code bases and I guess it depends
on your term of Legacy maybe a week old
code is Legacy code already but if we
think about a legacy code base whereby
no one in the organization still around
that coded that originally or this is
such old code no one has a clue no one
wants to change it first of all anyway
because the risk of damaging or or
altering the behavior but uh but yeah
lack of documentation making it
extremely hard for people to even know
even know what does what how do you
approach that kind of a
task it's a great question and I think
if we look at the very
extreme you have Legacy code bases that
are that were written decades ago in say
cobal fortron languages that aren't as
common today let's say startups don't
usually choose them to start writing
their software right but they're still
very prominent in
production yeah and the risk they're
also High when when you think about a
very large cobalt codebase usually runs
on some Mainframe and it processes some
Financial transactions so if someone
introduces a bug then you might find
yourself losing millions of dollars
right it's it's all of those extremes
together and usually the people who
wrote this code are no longer at the
company and there I think the pain is
really big but as you said you could
Define legacy code in different words
one definition would be a part of the
code no one knows or a part of the code
that only one person knows so they're a
bottleneck to any change here right in
either way I think the best approach and
what we advocate for is to start by
automating what you can and by that I
mean analyze the codebase and for that
we heavily rely on our static analysis
capabilities that are specific pair
language to make sure they're accurate
and top of that ler of language agnostic
algorithms for example that rank the
most important flows to explain in a
codebase if you're new to a codebase
what's the main flow what do you need to
understand first what are the and you
work that out statically or do you take
operational data in uh to to help you
with that so we do that statically uhuh
and we for multiple reasons but we want
this analysis to occur pretty fast and
also it could happen on the developer's
machine or at least the client's Network
because usually when deal with code it's
very
sensitive okay so we run static analysis
we find all of those interesting
elements then we decide what's important
to document at the first
step and there we want to automate the
process of getting everything that you
can understand from the code itself onto
I would say paper but obviously it's a
digital paper a document that would then
be kept up to date and so
on and then notice also that here there
is a gap in knowledge we might not know
yet right so you start by a high level
overview these are the components these
are the main flows now usually people
don't say Okay I want to understand this
codebase a toz right let's start reading
it doesn't work like that usually you
have a task at hand so we give them an
overview and then we allow allow them to
dive deeper in again swimming lingo to
dive deeper into a specific module or
feature and there they can either find
documentation we generated generate more
documents on the fly or ask questions
using a chat interface that we have
where AI shines again I think by that
you get a developer to get all the
context they need that you can
understand from code for solving the
issue then while they're solving it or
solving a bug introducing a new feature
we want to prompt them to document as
well or to extend the existing
documentation with additional knowledge
they now have yeah and I think the chat
interface is interesting there which is
something we didn't haven't really
touched upon just yet and I'm thinking
about it in two ways for the Legacy code
base it allows your developers to ask
questions of it and think this is great
but I don't understand this bit can you
tell can you expand on this because I
feel like this is a more important area
but equally when we think back to where
the data is in the developer's mind
rather than in the code base while the
developer's writing this is an
interesting point in time where a
developer can actually say this is good
documentation but you're missing a core
Point here do do you find developers
will prefer to to use the chat interface
to add to the documentation or do they
tend to just go straight in and say look
I'm gonna I'm G to add this
documentation into what you've already
added and then you can keep that up to
date going forward so we usually see
when people interact with the chat they
might iterate as you do with any AI
assistant then you get a good response
that is helpful and you can click create
a document from it and that's a draft
that they then edit in the document
editor we don't see people we see people
teach the AI like can you explain about
this more but when they want to document
it they usually do it in the
documentation
editor let's round this part of the
episode off before we jump into the deep
dive and let's think going forward a
little bit so obviously this is a real
this is one of the real problem s in
software development in and around
documentation just being poor generally
and for those who are watching on
YouTube I've got my Star Wars shirt
where underneath it says the Wrath of
Khan and if you haven't noticed that
then you're one of the folks that are
bad at reading documentation but uh I'm
one of those as well but for going
forward AI is also going to be used in
many other places of course in the
workflow including AI code generation
and the more AI generates a codebase for
us I guess the less people are going to
understand about I not just the
implementation but a lot of the a lot of
the kind of Niche parts of how the the
the project works I guess first of
all that removes a lot of the
information from the developer's mind or
at least it makes it higher level it
leans into various other parts of
documentation the documentation I guess
is more important in that respect
because the developer doesn't know as
much about the code but equally when we
think about code
documentation what's the point of code
document anymore because does the
developer need to read the code well not
really because the developer is not
writing it and at some point not going
to maintain it as much because the AI is
going to get more and more capable of
that so are we leaning more into that
space now where the code is going to
matter less as a result the code
documentation is going to matter less
however the project documentation is
going to matter a lot more because
developers are going to be that much
more disconnected from their code bases
is that how you see it or is there areas
that need to be added there I agree I
think that if we Define legacy code AS
code that no one in the organization
knows so if AI wrote the
code then immediately it's Legacy code
right and I agree there is this let's
say transitional period where the code
is still very much
important and then the code
documentation is more important and if
we get to or when we get to a future
where AI writes a lot of the but for us
I agree the project documentation is
going to be so much more important and
not only for humans AI assistants can
rely on documentation to generate better
code or to answer questions in a better
way we've tested different AI
assistants on the same code base with
and without swim documents and the
results are staggeringly different yeah
for code completion for code generation
for chat interface asking questions
right if you have a document explaining
something it's so much easier for any AI
agent every model to generate a good
answer than without the documentation so
I think we are actually experiencing now
a new role of
documentation documentation for coding
assistants or for AI
assistants really interesting and I
actually spoke with Devin from Dosey you
probably know and yeah one a couple of
the examples we talked about there is
how Devon can pull so much context from
that documentation
but of course documentation doesn't
always exist so sometimes it has to dip
into the code but then it's maybe even
pulling things that you work around that
shouldn't exist or that aren't
intentional and maybe suggesting to
users things that that they shouldn't be
doing or are perhaps not the path that
the the maintainer or the individual who
who it's outdated documentation that's
taken into account as the source of
Truth where it's just misleading right
and it's really hard for AI to
differentiate yeah so that's that's
super interesting so the drift is
actually will actually become that much
worse for those types of tools that are
relying upon that documentation being up
to date as a source of Truth which is
why we know people refer to code as the
source of as the source of truth right
and as prds and and specs more become
mainstream I guess in the future the
important documentation there is going
to be getting things out of people's
minds as to why they specified or why
they made decisions in that
specification
versus the fact that it was it's there
as well that that becomes the new
problem solving decisions and coding
decisions right and perhaps you would
want two types of documents like one
that is actual PRD in the sense that
this is what we wanted in the beginning
but another is like the working copy of
this purd and what the code looks like
now or what it does now given the
changing circumstances and requirements
that you introduced in time yeah this is
the
current reflection of the code what is
in the working copy right yeah and this
can AI to understand what's happening
now but if you want to understand the
history why it got to this place you
might want to track changes of the
document or see the original version
fascinating Omar very interesting uh
discussion and we can go in for much
much longer but let's jump into some
actual visuals that's it for this part
of the episode we're going to now jump
into YouTube only where we're going to
show a lot of the work flows here
including how personal the assisted
workflows can work as well as some of
the larger scale documentation can work
on projects that aren't documented so
let's jump into that and for those of
you were listening to the podcast jump
over to YouTube to view that and thanks
for tuning in we'll speak to you again
thank you very much thank you Simon
[Applause]
thanks for tuning in join us next time
on the AI native Dev brought to you by
tessla
[Music]